# **ALBERT PINTO**

San Francisco Bay Area | 925 640 3076 | albertpinto123@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/albert-pinto

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Seasoned leader with over 15 years of management experience, including 5+ years leveraging AI, data science, and machine learning. Successfully managed teams ranging from 8 to 50 members and worked with over 2000 fortune 500 customers.

#### Technical leadership expertise in

- **Direct the design, management, and execution of enterprise-wide AI technology tools**, maintaining high quality standards and managing the activities necessary to keep the technology support operations running seamlessly.
- **Build pioneering AI prototypes from scratch** drawing on expertise in the latest emerging technologies in artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML).
- **Drive strategic AI and data science initiatives** implementing effective cost controls, making resource allocation decisions, and improving the team's ability to deliver high-quality experiences to customers.
- **Guide executive teams to establish key success indicators** related to the data science, technical support, and quality assurance organizations, and report on performance metrics in ticketing and tracking systems.
- Manage the operational aspects of engineering and enterprise customer service as well as the assessment, identification, and implementation of strategies and technologies to enhance application performance.

#### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

# **SUPPORT VECTORS, Fremont CA**

An artificial intelligence (AI), big-data, machine-learning, and technical mentoring, product & consulting startup.

# Director of AI, Data Science and Machine Learning, Sep 2022 – Present

Spearhead the creation of scalable, enterprise-grade AI applications, cutting-edge platforms, and solutions, leading the charge in delivering innovative projects for a portfolio of 10 clients from new IT startups to SMB enterprises. Manage a dynamic 12-member engineering team in the U.S. and India, promoting a culture of data-driven innovation and operational excellence.

- Achieved over 90% of customer satisfaction on AI projects, expecting to double customers and revenue in the next year by tailoring products to meet the needs of clients utilizing various emerging AI technologies.
- Scheduled to unveil a minimum viable product (MVP) for an agentic multi-agent framework using AutoGen to simplify
  the creation and maintenance of large amounts of repetitious text.
- Enhanced multimodal semantic search with RAG (Retrieval Augmented Generation) capabilities by developing a vector database platform and advanced virtual assistants for two Silicon Valley startups and two Fortune 500 companies.
- Developed an end-to-end platform and AI assistant from scratch featuring functionality to integrate with other vector databases when needed, in the process of implementing this solution for three Silicon Valley startups.
- Delivered a unique convolutional neural network (CNN) model-based car identification solution for an IT startup.

# **WELKIN HEALTH, San Francisco CA**

An automated care management platform with \$5M annual revenue, 30 customers, and 1M patients.

#### Head of Data, Technical Support, and Quality Assurance, Sep 2020 - Sep 2022

Led an 8-person team on data science, end to end support, quality assurance, and performance of a global healthcare platform including a comprehensive portfolio of SaaS products and customizable API solutions hosted on AWS. Compiled and presented monthly executive summaries on product, support, and customer data, ensuring informed decision-making.

- Improved customer satisfaction ratings from 65% to 95% in 8 months by spearheading the recruitment of a new support team of 4 engineers in the Ukraine and building a new and scalable technical support system.
- Established a successful revenue stream by developing advanced data science solutions, reporting, and metrics tailored for enterprise customers, alongside basic standard metrics for other customers using Sisense.
- Reduced resolution time by over 30% through training and coaching the QA engineering team to efficiently support new products and set up on-call processes while offboarding and migrating customers from old systems.
- Ensured early notification to customers regarding outages and provided regular updates on expected resolutions by devising an effective testing plan for all features and defects.

#### **40VER,INC, Greater Los Angeles Area**

An online printing business that generated \$300M in annual ecommerce revenues.

Senior Manager of Content Strategy & Engineering, Aug 2017 - Aug 2020

Led a team of 8 engineers, reporting to the Chief Technology Officer (CTO).

- Improved website visibility and organic traffic by establishing an effective SEO strategy, incorporating structured metadata, AdWords, and insights from customer behavior.
- Streamlined content management processes through assisting with the design and managing the transition from an in-house dotCMS to Contentful CMS, ensuring efficient content and asset handling.
- Enhanced user experience with real-time content updates by architecting and managing a library for real-time content delivery via Contentful's APIs, implementing secure roles, entitlements, and authentication mechanisms.
- Boosted performance 15% and reduced costs 33% playing a key role in rolling out a new online platform using ReactJS, Node.js, Postgres, and Contentful.

#### DELL/EMC/Documentum, Pleasanton CA

An enterprise content management platform company serving large and medium fortune 500 companies.

#### Senior Manager of Engineering, Mar 2008 - Aug 2017

Directed support engineering and operations teams for the Americas generating \$600M revenue. Charged with rectifying defects, handling release requests, offering consultancy services, and addressing feature inquiries. Conducted high-stakes communications with C-level executives regarding escalations, promoting transparency and accountability at all levels.

- Achieved 80% issue resolution within a two-weeks successfully resolving over 3,000 critical customer issues across diverse product lines that impacted 2,000+ clients by crafting and implementing decisive action plans.
- Established a customer-centric engineering group providing global product support for a customer base of 5,000 leading and synchronizing the efforts of 100+ engineers on 25 domestic and 20 international engineering teams.
- End to End Support for numerous Fortune 500 corporations, including Walmart, USAA, Bank of America, Chevron, Eli Lilly, BHP, and Boeing, each contributing more than a million dollars in support and sustenance revenue.
- Recognized with Rockstar and Gold Customer Service Awards for a USAA project that involved enhancing product support for mixed versions of clients and content repositories; collaborated cross-functionally on a groundbreaking innovation that earned multiple patents and was highlighted at the EMC World Conference.
- Boosted customer satisfaction and safeguarded the trust and loyalty of valued clients including Intel, Cisco, John
  Wiley, and Pearson by deploying a solution that rectified over 255 critical product defects and feature requests;
  enhanced the platform and enabled client applications to be fully compatible with DITA technology.
- Spearheaded a comprehensive overhaul of the content repository platform yielding 25 new patents and setting new industry benchmarks; attracted the World Bank as a new client and generated over \$25M in license fees.

#### Additional Roles with Documentum/DELL EMC:

- Manager, Web Content Management (WCM) Group
- Diversity, Equality & Inclusion, Asian Circle West coast, Vice President
- Lead Architect for IT, Development and Applications Team

#### **EDUCATION & CREDENTIALS**

B.S & M.S., Computer Science and Engineering | Manipal Institute of Technology, India

#### **Certifications**

- Multi AI Agent Systems with crewAI, DeepLearning.AI, Sep 2024
- Al Agentic Design Patterns with AutoGen, DeepLearning.Al, Aug 2024
- Fine tuning large language models, DeepLearning.AI 2024
- Al Neural Networks & Generative certification, SupportVectors 2024
- Basic and Advanced AI LLM projects, Certification, SupportVectors 2024
- Intermediate & Advanced Deep Learning AI certification, SupportVectors, 2022
- Data Wrangling & Visualization in Python, SupportVectors, 2023
- Six Sigma Yellow Belt

### **Technical Skills**

- AI/ML: Generative AI, Large Language Models (LLMs), Natural Language Processing (NLP), Prompt Engineering, Neural Nets, AI Search, FAISS, Transformers, Lang Chain technologies, Vector Databases, Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG), Adaptive RAG (ARAG), voice synthesis (Eleven Labs' technology), GAN, Llama-Index, Autogen, CrewAI, Llava, CLIP, BLIP, CNN, RNN and others
- Agentic Frameworks: Autogen, CrewAI, Langchain & Llama-Index using tree of thought and Chain of thought.
- Deep Learning Frameworks: PyTorch,TensorFlow,
- Compute Frameworks: Ray, Spark/Hadoop,

Github repository: https://github.com/albertpinto/